Chapter "Polygonal Structures"
Although we are mostly interested in surfaces, the process of folding naturally
leads us to more general structures. Therefore, the most general structure that 
we consider in this package is a polygonal complex 
(a generalisation of simplicial surfaces and complexes).



    Polygonal Complexes are structures that are build from polygons (for the exact
    definition, see section ...), like
    [Picture from the start of the introduction]
    Since we are especially interested in surfaces we need a way to recognize
    them. For technical reasons we split this process into two separate steps,
    with the ramified polygonal surfaces as the intermediate structure betwee
    polygonal complexes and polygons surfaces.
    In many cases the definitions and algorithms simplify if we only consider
    triangles instead of general polygons. For this reason we also have equivalents
    of these structures that are only build from triangles. We can summarize
    the relationships graphically (higher means more general):

    Picture:
        Polygonal Complex
                 |
                 |                       Triangular Complex
                 |                           |
        Ramified Polygonal Surface           |
                 |                           |
                 |                      Ramified simplicial surface
                 |                           |
        Polygonal Surface                    |
                                        Simplicial surface
    


Section "Polygonal and Triangular complexes"
A polygonal complex is defined by a two-dimensional incidence geometry with some
regularity conditions. We will exemplify this by the following surface:

                    V3 -------E4-------- V4
              E2 /  |                    |
                /   |                    |
              V1 F1 E3        F2         E5
                \   |                    |
              E1 \  |                    |
                    V2 -------E6-------- V5
        [without labels]
In a two-dimensional incidence geometry we have the set V of vertices, E of edges
and F of faces. If we label our picture [as above] we have the sets
    V = {V1,V2,V3,V4,V5}
    E = {E1,E2,E3,E4,E5,E6}
    F = {F1,F2}
These sets can't encode the surface on their own. We also need the relations 
between vertices, edges and faces. For that we define a transitive relation on
    V x E    +    V x F    +   E x F
where (a,b) is in the relation if and only if a is incident to b. Since the
relation is transitive, it is only necessary to define VxE and ExF.
In our example this relation would be generated by
    { (V1,E1), (V1,E2),  }
    {  }

To guarantee that the edges of this incidence geometry behave like the
edges of the picture we impose this condition:
    1) For every edge there are exactly two different vertices that are incident to it.

We need a similar condition for the faces but it is a bit more complicated:
    2) For each face the number of incident vertices is equal to the number of
        incident edges. Additionally they can be ordered v1,...,vk and e1,...,ek
        such that vi and v{i+1} are incident to ei (indices are read modulo k).

Since these conditions still allow F to be empty without V being empty, we enforce
the condition
    3) Every vertex is incident to at least one face.

A polygonal complex is now just a two-dimensional incidence geometry that satisfies
these three conditions.




Section "Ramified Polygonal and Simplicial Surfaces"



Section "Polygonal and Simplicial Surfaces"



